Register of the Inez Richardson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Inez Richardson papers
1905-1963
1933-1958
XX001
Hoover Institution Archives
25 manuscript boxes (10.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, speeches and writings, photographs, and printed matter relating to international relations; education; the role of radio and television in education; the 1930 White House Conference on Child Health and Protection; American Higher Education conferences; Herbert Hoover; the administration of Stanford University and the Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace; the Revolution and the Development of International Relations Project at the Hoover Institution; and the Stanford Listening Post and the Civil Affairs Training School at Stanford University during World War II.
Richardson, Inez, d. 1965.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Tower of Peace radio broadcasts, Hoover Institution Archives
White House Conference on Child Health and Protection records, Hoover Institution Archives
Stanford Listening Post records, Hoover Institution Archives
Ray Lyman Wilbur papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
From the 1930s to the early 1960s, Inez Richardson worked for the Hoover Institution and Stanford University in a myriad of roles, from executive assistant, coordinator and liaison for foreign visitors to Stanford, and faculty member of the Radio-Television Institute, to director of the Stanford Listening Post. In addition, Richardson was an assistant to Stanford University president Ray Lyman Wilbur and curator of the Ray Lyman Wilbur collection on Social Problems at the Hoover Institution.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Inez Richardson papers document Richardson's career with the Hoover Institution and Stanford University. The collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, reports, speeches and writings, conference proceedings, photographs, notes, and printed matter. While the bulk of the collection details administrative aspects of Stanford University and the Hoover Institution, many of the files reflect Richardson's participation in and administration of many of the Hoover Institution's and Ray Lyman Wilbur's interests, including education, housing, healthcare, radio, and foreign relations. Also included are files related to Stanford University's participation in World War II with the Stanford Listening Post and CATS (Civil Affairs Training School), and the university's relationship with the Office of War Information.
Richardson's original order, file names, and cross references have been maintained.
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; Stanford University.; White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (1930: Washington, D.C.); International education.; United States. Civil Affairs Training School, Stanford University.; Radio in education.; Television in education.; International relations.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Stanford Listening Post.; Radio broadcasting--East Asia.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; World War, 1939-1945--Occupied territories.; Military government.; Child welfare--United States.; Child health services--United States.; Elite (Social sciences)
- Career Subject File, 1933-1963
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of reports, correspondence, programs, notes, drafts, photographs, and printed matter. Maintains the original alphabetical order designated by the creator.
  - A, 1946-1963 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - AAUN (American Association for the United Nations), 1949-1952 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - AFME (American Friends of the Middle East), 1952-1961 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - American Child Health Association, 1933-1937 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - American Social Hygiene Association, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - American Universities Field Staff, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 1:6-8)
    Includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, summaries and reports by Edward Bayne, Boyd Compton, Edwin Munger, and Albert Ravenholt.
  - Asia Foundation, newsletters, 1954-1960 (Box-folder 1:9)
    General note
    See also: Committee for a Free Asia.
  - B, 1934-1957 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Barnard, Harry E., 1934-1946 (Box-folder 2:2)
    See also: White House Conference on Child Health and Protection.
  - Bay Area TV Association, 1950s (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Better Homes in America, 1933-1936 (Box-folder 2:4)
    Also contains reports for the Wilbur collection.
  - Bittner, Mark, 1950-1952 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - C, 1933-1957 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - California Conservation Council, 1933-1951 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3:1)
    See also: RADIR project.
  - CATS (Civil Affairs Training School), 1943-1955
    - Correspondence and notes, 1944-1955 (Box-folder 3:2-3)
    - Europe, 1944-1949 (Box-folder 3:4)
    - Japan, undated (Box-folder 3:5)
    - Reports, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 3:6)
    - Budgets (Box-folder 3:7)
  - CBS (Columbia Broadcast System), 1939-1959 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - CCIS (Civil Communications Intelligence School) budget, 1945 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - CCIS, Japan, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Contract forms, undated (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Committee for a Free Asia, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 4:2)
    See also: Asia Foundation.
  - D, 1936-1961 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - E, 1949-1959 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - F, 1941-1957 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Faculty reports, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Fisher, Harold, 1936-1957 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Ford Foundation, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Ford survey correspondence, 1951 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Foreign visitors, 1950-1961
    - American Council on Education, 1957 (Box-folder 4:10)
    - Eisenhower exchange, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4:11)
    - Annual reports, 1956-1960 (Box-folder 4:12)
    - Foreign visitors, 1951-1955 (Box-folder 5:1)
      Includes news clippings, biographies, schedules, announcements, and correspondence regarding education exchange.
    - Photographs, visits by Russian editors and Prince Albert of Belgium, undated (Box-folder 5:2)
    - Foreign student adviser and student program, 1947, 1957, 1961 (Box-folder 5:3)
    - ASSU (Associated Students of Stanford University), 1951 (Box-folder 5:4)
    - Foreign visitors, countries A through Z, at Hoover Institution and Library, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 5:5-7)
    - Charles B. Roberts, Liberia, Eisenhower exchange fellow, 1956 (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Celal Bayer, President of Turkey, 1954 (Box-folder 6:2)
    - University Committee, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 6:3)
    - Foreign Visitors Committee, correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 6:4)
    - Iranian visitor, photographs, undated (Box-folder 6:5)
    - Foreign scholars and other visitors, 1956 (Box-folder 6:6)
    - Abdul Rahman Al-Bazzaz, Dean of University of Baghdad Law School, Iraq, 1956 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - G, 1938-1955 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Glover, Katherine, 1934-1952 (Box-folder 7:2)
    Correspondence. See also: White House Conference on Child Health and Protection.
  - Governor's conference on educational television, 1952 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - H, 1939, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Hoover Institution and Library - History and Ray Lyman Wilbur collection on social problems, 1934-1963 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - I, 1934-1937, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Institute of International Education, 1951-1953 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Institute of International Relations, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - J, 1938 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - K, 1937-1955 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - KPIX, 1952 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - KQED, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - KZSU, 1948-1951 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Kerr, George H., Ryukyus and other Pacific Area studies, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Kitagawa, Kay, 1942-1963 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - L, 1939-1954 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - M, 1934-1959 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Motion Picture Research Council, re: closing of the San Francisco office, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 8:9-10)
  - MP (motion pictures) for Wilbur collection, 1935-1945 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - N, 1933-1956 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - NAB (National Association of Broadcasters), 1943-1953 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - NAEB (National Association of Educational Broadcasters), 1951-1953 (Box-folder 9:4)
  - NBC (National Broadcasting Company), 1939-1959 (Box-folder 9:5-11)
  - National Council of Teachers of English, 1953 (Box-folder 10:1)
  - National Youth Administration, 1937-1941 (Box-folder 10:2)
  - O, 1933-1952 (Box-folder 10:3)
  - P, 1944-1951 (Box-folder 10:4)
  - Palo Alto Free World Forum, 1942 (Box-folder 10:5)
  - President's Conference on Home Building and Home Ownership, 1931, 1940 (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Q, 1951 (Box-folder 10:7)
  - R, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 10:8)
  - Radio and TV at Stanford - Hoover Institution cooperation and participation, 1938-1940, 1948 (Box-folder 10:9)
  - RADIR (Revolution and the Development of International Relations) project, preliminary drafts, 1959 (Box-folder 10:10)
  - Richardson, Inez, 1933-1962 (Box-folder 10:11)
  - Richey, Lawerence, 1950s (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Rosenberg Fund, grants and correspondence, re: Scott and Mysels Projects, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - S, 1936-1957 (Box-folder 11:3)
  - Schenck, Hubert, 1956 (Box-folder 11:4)
  - School of Health Education Service Joint Committee (AMA-HEA), 1936-1937 (Box-folder 11:5)
  - School of Naval Adminstration (SONA), 1946-1951 (Box-folder 11:6)
  - Scott, Charles (Chas) Craven, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 11:7)
  - Service letters, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 12:1)
  - Social Trends Committee (President's Research Committee on Social Trends), 1934 (Box-folder 12:2)
  - Sokol, Anthony E., 1952, 1954, 1957 (Box-folder 12:3)
  - Stanford University - ASSU (Associated Students Stanford University), 1933-1961
    - Pamphlets, 1950s (Box-folder 12:4)
    - Typescript, undated (Box-folder 12:5)
    - Stanford Research Institute, 1951, 1956 (Box-folder 12:6)
    - The Stanford Survey of Behavioral Sciences, 1954 (Box-folder 12:7)
    - News clippings, 1946-1961 (Box-folder 13:1)
    - Department of Athletics, 1950 (Box-folder 13:2)
    - Committee for Research in the Social Sciences, 1953-1954 (Box-folder 13:3)
    - Survey Committee, 1953 (Box-folder 13:4)
    - Director of Information, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 13:5)
    - Distaff Club, 1951-1955 (Box-folder 13:6)
    - Fiftieth anniversary (of Stanford University), articles, 1941 (Box-folder 13:7)
    - General Secretary Office, 1955 (Box-folder 13:8)
    - Guide service, 1947, 1956 (Box-folder 13:9)
    - Health and services plan, 1953 (Box-folder 13:10)
    - Press, 1953, 1955 (Box-folder 13:11)
      Relates to Stanford University Press and publishing.
    - Public exercises (Committee on Public Exercises), 1947-1957 (Box-folder 13:12)
    - Registrar's Office, 1953 (Box-folder 13:13)
    - Interdepartmental memoranda and correspondence, 1933-1960 (Box-folder 13:14)
  - T, 1943, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 14:1)
  - Toynbee, A. J., speeches, 1950 (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Trust Territories of the Pacific, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 14:3)
  - U, 1934-1957 (Box-folder 14:4)
  - UNESCO (United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization), start of collection to honor Grayson N. Kefauver, 1947 (Box-folder 14:5)
  - United Nations conference, 1945 (Box-folder 14:6)
  - United States Army - miscellaneous, 1951 (Box-folder 14:7)
  - United States Government Office of Education, 1936-1959 (Box-folder 14:8)
  - United States Navy, 1942 (Box-folder 14:9)
  - University Association for Professional Radio Education, 1949 (Box-folder 14:10)
  - University of Denver, 1951 (Box-folder 14:11)
  - University President's Office, 1949-1959 (Box-folder 14:12)
  - V, 1941-1961 (Box-folder 14:13)
  - Velliotes, George, 1951-1955 (Box-folder 14:14)
  - W, 1939-1961 (Box-folder 14:15)
  - Western Conference on Government, 1934 (Box-folder 14:16)
  - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection, 1933-1962 (Box-folder 15:1-5)
    Includes committee members and personnel records, general correspondence, reports, memoranda, and correspondence with George Hastings, Secretary to President Hoover. Richardson noted that these files are records collected after 1933, when the conference documents were transferred to the Hoover Library, and she has made annotations regarding where related documents may be found in the collection.
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman, correspondence, 1933-1963 (Box-folder 15:6)
  - World Affairs Council and Radio Committee, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 16:1)
  - Y, 1953-1963 (Box-folder 16:2)
- American Higher Education Conference Materials, 1929-1958
  Consists of conference proceedings, administrative planning records, correspondence, and printed matter regarding the America Higher Education conference at Stanford in 1958.
  - Plans for conference, correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 16:3)
  - Plans for conference, meeting minutes and notes, 1957 (Box-folder 16:4)
  - Conference reports, drafts, and notes, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 16:5)
  - Program drafts, 1958 (Box-folder 16:6)
  - Conference programs, 1958 (Box-folder 17:1)
  - Fact-finding studies, reports, 1929-1945 (Box-folder 17:2)
  - Crowley-Sterling statements, 1957 (Box-folder 17:3)
  - Preliminary budgets, 1958 (Box-folder 17:4)
  - Fulbright scholars, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 17:5)
  - Invitations and replies, 1958 (Box-folder 17:6-7)
  - List of participants, 1958 (Box-folder 17:8)
  - Forms file, 1958 (Box-folder 18:1)
  - Thank you letters, 1958 (Box-folder 18:2)
  - General correspondence, 1958 (Box-folder 18:3)
  - Letters received for Richardson, 1958 (Box-folder 18:4)
  - Conference materials, programs, schedules, and ephemera, 1958 (Box-folder 18:5)
  - Conference speeches, 1958 (Box-folder 18:6)
  - Conference photographs, 1958 (Box-folder 18:7)
  - Conference tours, 1958 (Box-folder 18:8)
  - Dinner arrangements, 1958 (Box-folder 18:9)
  - Past American Higher Education conferences, 1953-1958
    - List of delegates, 1957 (Box-folder 19:1)
    - Reports and programs, 1956-1957 (Box-folder 19:2)
    - Planning committee materials, 1953-1956 (Box-folder 19:3)
    - Conference evaluations, 1954-1958 (Box-folder 19:4)
    - "Conference on Education and Student Life in the United States," University of Chicago, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 19:5)
    - Miscellaneous programs and pamphlets, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 19:6)
- Hoover Institution and Library File, 1905-1959
  Consists mainly of correspondence, notes, and printed matter for interdepartmental communication and planning regarding the administration, publicity, and courses of the Institution.
  - Hoover booklet drafts, 1955 (Box-folder 19:7)
  - Hoover pamphlet and leaflet revisions, 1955 (Box-folder 19:8)
  - History of the Hoover Institution, 1931-1957 (Box-folder 20:1-2)
    Includes drafts, pamphlets, correspondence, and news clippings.
  - Tower carillon, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 20:3)
  - Tower building dedication, 1938-1950 (Box-folder 20:4)
  - "The Story of the Great Hoover War Library at Stanford University," by Neil Wilson, undated (Box-folder 20:5)
  - Galleys of "Tower to Peace" publication, 1945, 1955 (Box-folder 20:6)
  - Visitors within the United States, miscellcaneous items, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 20:7)
  - Staff bulletin, Tower Talk, 1952-1953 (Box-folder 20:8)
  - Herbert Hoover files, 1933-1958
    - Hoover, Herbert, 1933-1957 (Box-folder 21:1)
      Mainly consists of correspondence with Bernice Miller, Herbert Hoover’s personal secretary.
    - Conservation with Herbert Hoover, film, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 21:2-3)
    - Letter from Herbert Hoover to General Pershing, 1942 December 14 (Box-folder 21:4)
  - Appreciations, 1952-1956 (Box-folder 21:5)
  - Weekly planners, 1946-1956 (Box-folder 21:6)
  - Card files, 1950s (Box-folder 21:7)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1958 (Box-folder 22:1)
  - Christmas cards, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 22:2)
  - Publicity, 1957 (Box-folder 22:3)
  - News clippings, 1943,1959 (Box-folder 22:4)
  - Research and RADIR (Revolution and the Development of International Relations) project, 1948 (Box-folder 22:5)
  - Film stored at MGM, correspondence, 1955 (Box-folder 22:6)
  - Conferences, 1957 (Box-folder 22:7)
  - Stanford and course offerings, 1905-1958
    - Course 202: World Communications, 1951 Summer (Box-folder 22:8)
    - Course 226: Communication seminar, 1941-1942 Winter (Box-folder 22:9)
    - Course 206, 1951 Summer (Box-folder 22:10)
    - University schedules and bulletins, 1938-1959 (Box-folder 22:11)
      Includes documents on speech and drama, speech therapy, and television courses.
    - Special discussion meetings, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 23:1-2)
    - Far Western Slavic Conference, 1959 April (Box-folder 23:3)
    - Committee on Foreign Students and Visitors, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 23:4)
    - Radio and television, 1956-1959 (Box-folder 23:5)
    - Emergency Conservation School, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 23:6-7)
    - "A Decennial of Stanford Song,", 1905 (Box-folder 24:1)
- Stanford Listening Post and Office of War Information File, 1940-1950
  Consists of reports, administrative and interdepartmental documents, correspondence, project transcripts and lists, and broadcast notes regarding the establishment of the Stanford Listening Post, its transition to the Federal Communications Committee's (FCC) supervision from 1941 to 1943, and transmission of American broadcasts of the United States Office of War Information (OWI) to the Far East from 1942 to 1945.
  - Stanford Listening Post, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 24:2-4, 25:1)
    Includes memoranda, correspondence, administrative documents, broadcast notes, and lists regarding the Listening Post program. The short wave radio recordings mainly concern Chunking, Tokyo, Saigon, and other Pacific area cities.
  - Federal Communications Committee, Wakefield, Ray, 1939-1950 (Box-folder 25:2)
  - Office of War Information, Coordinator of Information, re: Pacific Area work, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 25:3)
  - Office of War Information, Stanford contract work, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 25:4)